A fraction is part of a whole.
Here is one whole bar.
Cut it into 4 equal parts.
Colour in 3 parts.
We write this as three quarters.
The bottom number: how many equal parts in total.
The top number: how many parts we colour in.
The parts MUST be equal.
This bar has 4 parts, but they are not equal.
So the shaded part is NOT one quarter.
Different fractions can be the same amount.
Half of the bar.
Two quarters.
Four eighths.
Look! The coloured part is the same length.
These are called equivalent fractions.
Same amount, different names.
To make an equivalent fraction...
...multiply the top AND the bottom by the same number.
We can also go the other way.
This is called simplifying.
Six eighths. Can we use fewer, bigger parts?
Find the HCF of 6 and 8. It is 2.
Divide the top and the bottom by 2.
Six eighths is the same as three quarters!
Whatever you do to the top, do to the bottom!